Guide to the Middle Eastern Manuscripts Collection, circa 9th century - circa 1920
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Middle Eastern Manuscripts Collection
circa 9th century - circa 1920
Vassar College. Library
13 codices, 5 leaves
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Codices and leaves of manuscripts and illuminated manuscripts from different parts of the Middle East, primarily of the Qur'an and excerpts of the Qur'an. Also includes scholarly and literary works.
Scope and Content Note
Codices and leaves of manuscripts and illuminated manuscripts from different parts of the Middle East, primarily of the Qur'an and excerpts of the Qur'an. Also includes scholarly and literary works.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Cuneiform Tablets
The Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection contains Armenian manuscript leaves.
Papyrus Collection
The Ruth Lamb Atkinson Papers includes Persian and Sanskrit manuscript leaves and illustrations.
Subject Headings
Subjects:
Illumination of books and manuscripts, Arab; Illumination of books and manuscripts, Iranian; Manuscripts, Arabic; Manuscripts, Armenian; Manuscripts, Egyptian; Manuscripts, Iranian; Manuscripts, Persian; Manuscripts, Syriac; Qur'an--Manuscripts
Document Types:
Codices (bound manuscripts); Illuminated manuscripts; Manuscripts (documents); Qur'ans
VCL Categories:
Middle Eastern, Asian, Ethiopian, and Russian Manuscripts
Encoding Information
Encoded by Emma Gronbeck, January 2024.
Acquisition Information
Item 3 was the gift of Janet (Bartlett) Cartwright (VC 1921), Jul 1957.
Item 4 was the gift of William Bancroft Hill, 1932.
Item 6 was the gift of Ethel M. Fair (VC 1906), Nov 1971. Given to her by the Council and Faculties of the American University at Cairo in 1952.
Item 7 was the gift of Mildred E. Cook, 1959.
Items 11-14, 16 and 17 were the bequest of Frederick F. Thompson, 1924.
Item 10 was the gift of Ada Thurston (VC 1880), 1939.
Item 18 was the gift of Helen (Morgenthau) Fox (VC 1905), 1940.
Series List
- Series I. Arabic Manuscripts, 10th century - circa 1920
- Series II. Armenian Manuscripts, circa 15th century - 1672
- Series III. Persian Manuscripts, circa 1582 - circa 1819, undated
- Series IV. Syriac Manuscripts, 9th century - 11th century
- Series V. Turkish Manuscripts, Before 1700 - circa 1800
Item List
- Series I. Arabic Manuscripts
  - A Leaf from a Qur'an, in Arabic (Kufic script), circa 1175; [Previously Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection, Item 51] (Item 1)
  - Kufic Prayer [Persia?], 10th century; [framed leaf in wooden case, 16 x 10 cm] (Item 2)
  - Qur'an, in Arabic, circa 1849; [18 x 13 cm] (Item 3)
  - Qur'an, in Arabic, [14th century?]; [23 x 13 cm] (Item 4)
  - Qur'an, in Arabic, circa 1800-1920; [2 volumes, 22 cm] (Item 5 [BP100.3 1800z (Grille)])
  - Qur'an, [in Arabic?], undated; [23 x 13 cm] (Item 6)
  - Qur'an, in Arabic [Egypt (Cairo)], 18th century (last quarter); [See Ernest Sturm Collection, Volume 6 ]
  - Qur'an, excerpts and other poetry, in Arabic [Persia], circa 1843 (1259 Hijiri); [18 x 11 cm] (Item 7)
- Series II. Armenian Manuscripts
  - A Leaf from a Praxapostolos, in Armenian, 15th or 16th century; [See Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection, Item 11 ]
  - Two Leaves from a Homilary, in Armenian [Iran (Isfahan)], 1671–1672; [See Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection, Items 52-53 ]
  - Five Leaves from a Homilary, in Armenian [Iran (Isfahan)], 1671-1672; [See Nicholas B. Scheetz Manuscripts Collection, MS 29a-e ]
- Series III. Persian Manuscripts
  - A Leaf from a Prayer Book [Persia], 1700; [Previously Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection, Item 73] (Item 8)
  - A Leaf from a Qur'an [Persia], 1700; [Previously Medieval and Renaissance Manuscripts Collection, Item 70] (Item 9)
  - A Leaf from a Qur'an, in Farsi or Persian, undated (Item 10)
  - [Ali, Meer?], Manuscript Book [Persia (Meshed, Khorassav)], circa 1582 (990 Hijiri); [24 x 16 cm] (Item 11)
  - Book of Fiction [Persia?], circa 1740 (1153 Hijiri); [27 x 15 cm] (Item 12)
  - Dahlavi, Amir Khosrow, Book of Leili and Majnoon [Persia?], [circa 1750?]; [31 x 20 cm] (Item 13)
  - Rashti, Agha Hussein, Book of Poetry [Persia?], circa 1819 (1234 Hijiri?); [24 x 14 cm] (Item 14)
- Series IV. Syriac Manuscripts
  - The Peshitta, in Syriac, 9th century - 11th century; [225 leaves, unbound (4 boxes)] (Item 15)
- Series V. Turkish Manuscripts
  - Book of Astronomy, in Turkish [Persia?], [Before 1700]; [32 x 22 cm] (Item 16)
  - Book of Geography, in Turkish [Persia?], [Before 1800]; [31 x 21 cm] (Item 17)
  - Prayer Book, in Turkish and Arabic (Naskh script), circa 1800; [15 x 11 cm] (Item 18)